Dr. Karan Mittal: Namaste, everyone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I welcome you all to Day 5 of our Introduction Module Level 1 course.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And we have, up till now, we have seen a few aspects of Indian psychological frameworks, and today's day would be more about getting into the basic, very basic framework of Ayurveda.
Dr. Karan Mittal: seeing the four Purusharthas, and also getting very deep into the Panchosha model of how to use it in therapy. So that's the plan for today. Without delay, I would like to just start the PPT and…
Dr. Karan Mittal: quite privy to kind of…
Govinda Das ji: Yes.
Govinda Das ji: Once again, welcome everybody. So, we will…
Govinda Das ji: We are seeing the Indian module of Manasikatha mindset.
Govinda Das ji: And we were seeing the foundational idea from our Dharma Shastra.
Govinda Das ji: the human drive, according to the Western theology, Western idea.
Govinda Das ji: Right, there is will to pleasure, will to power, and will to meaning.
Govinda Das ji: So, Freud, the psychologist, he said.
Govinda Das ji: The entire creation, entire mindset of human being, Is directed towards pleasure.
Govinda Das ji: So you've found… In his psychology.
Govinda Das ji: That we always look for pleasure.
Govinda Das ji: We act to feel good and avoid pain. That is the purpose of human existence, according to
Govinda Das ji: Freud, and became… it became the theory of will to pleasure.
Govinda Das ji: And therefore, we can see the Western civilization
Govinda Das ji: The entire system is driven in such a way to avoid inconvenience and increase Pleasure.
Govinda Das ji: Purely connected to… titillating the senses.
Govinda Das ji: Then there was Adler and Nitze.
Govinda Das ji: Right? Will to power, to such an extent.
Govinda Das ji: Nitze, going beyond Plato also, the Greek philosopher.
Govinda Das ji: They created two kinds of morality, the feminine morality and the masculine morality.
Govinda Das ji: The feminine morality is the morality of compassion, kindness, Being a follower.
Govinda Das ji: And the masculine morality was the morality of power Enterprising…
Govinda Das ji: Right? Standing on your own without being a follower.
Govinda Das ji: So he saw that only power functions.
Govinda Das ji: In fact, Nitche said, When you kill a butterfly, that's a… crime.
Govinda Das ji: But when you kill a cockroach, Right?
Govinda Das ji: Nobody cares.
Govinda Das ji: Because butterfly… Has some meaning.
Govinda Das ji: A cockroach is useless.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, we act to overcome weakness and gain mastery. In fact, Vishmade dev also
Govinda Das ji: Did mention something about this, but not independent.
Govinda Das ji: than Viktor Frankl.
Govinda Das ji: In his book, In Search of Meaning.
Govinda Das ji: Right? He saw everything. If there is a meaning in suffering, there has to be meaning. If there is meaning in pleasure, there has to be meaning in suffering also.
Govinda Das ji: So he said, let us find meaning.
Govinda Das ji: Unfortunately, most of the time, these three were… Independently existing.
Govinda Das ji: Sometime they try to integrate, but mostly, apparently they appeared as if they are… they are in conflict with each other.
Govinda Das ji: On the other hand, when we study, the core idea of
Govinda Das ji: the Indian knowledge system, the Baharate Vichyardara next, right?
Govinda Das ji: There is no… there is no conflict.
Govinda Das ji: There is Dharma, There is Arpa, there is karma, and there is moksha.
Govinda Das ji: In fact, generally, when you study Mahabharata, Raman, and other literature, they focus on three Varga.
Govinda Das ji: You must have heard 3 Varga, 3 Varga, 3 Virgo. What are these 3 Virgo? 3 Varga is Dharma.
Govinda Das ji: Right? Alignment with the nature's Law.
Govinda Das ji: In this frame, all other three will function. What is Eartha? ARTA is basically finding power through resources.
Govinda Das ji: And karma is pleasure. So, Dharma is… Will for meaning?
Govinda Das ji: Artha is will for power, and karma is willpower, pleasure, but they're not separately existing. Today's Sita Nami.
Govinda Das ji: Lord Ramachandra, when he was speaking to Bharat, he made a very interesting point. He said, hey, Bharat, when you rule.
Govinda Das ji: Your Dharma should not conflict with your artha.
Govinda Das ji: And your arata should not conflict with your dharma.
Govinda Das ji: Alright, one of the questions when people ask, Why, in India.
Govinda Das ji: There is so much of poverty, and that… and why there is so much of…
Govinda Das ji: Disparity, extreme disparity is there.
Govinda Das ji: So one philosopher said the experience… the great disparity is there, because consciously, unconsciously, we glorify poverty.
Govinda Das ji: Consciously, unconsciously, poverty is glorified.
Govinda Das ji: Artificial giving up things is glorified.
Govinda Das ji: But when you glorify something which is not natural.
Govinda Das ji: that much more you become attracted to the pleasures of life. So there is a conflict between giving up everything and having greed for everything.
Govinda Das ji: Right? There is a conflict between Vedanta and Veda. Veda focuses on life, Vedanta focuses on living life.
Govinda Das ji: They don't focus like that. People made it appear like that.
Govinda Das ji: You know, being driven by… pessimistic ideas, which is not part of the scripture.
Govinda Das ji: Therefore, dharma, artha, karma, when they are practiced properly, Great Naragmani told Yujishtir, He said
Govinda Das ji: Timely, arthr, timely, bogar, timely, karma.
Govinda Das ji: Will give rise to timely moksha.
Govinda Das ji: These are deeper subjects.
Govinda Das ji: Alright, we're only touching upon this, because we need to go to the next one, which is Ayurved and Panchakosha. But understand, they are not in conflict with each other, they are integrated.
Govinda Das ji: They are not… creating… difficulty, They are non-confusing, And progressive in life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so I would like to just add, like Prabhji mentioned, whether it's Freud, whether it's, let's say, whether it's Trankel, everyone focused on just one area, and went to the depth of it, and kind of conceptualized their whole theory around that. Like, Freud was about pleasure. So right until the age of birth, he went until that
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, particular period, and found out where the pleasure was hampered in the child's life, so that whatever issue is showing up right now over your… in the adult's life. So it was…
Dr. Karan Mittal: it was focused on just one aspect, but when we see the four Purusharathas, like, Arthha could be, like, you know, the self-esteem self, or karma could be happiness, Dharma and Moksha kind of giving the substratum to the whole thing. So when we look at this, the human being in a therapy from these
Dr. Karan Mittal: four dimensions, we see what is lost, whether it's the strength that is lost because of premature giving up of
Dr. Karan Mittal: pleasures, etc, or whether the happiness is lost, or whether the substratum, the ethical framework is lost. We try to figure out what is lost, and by, you know, counseling, generally.
Dr. Karan Mittal: nudging the client, we try to bring in that framework into the client's life to start balancing the four dimensions that we spoke of. So, until now was the, you know, whatever slides we missed in day four, and now we get into the Ayurvedic and the Panchk Kosha.
Dr. Karan Mittal: frameworks, so… So, if you see from an Ayurvedic perspective, sometimes we take Ayurved just to be
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, the three doshas, and healing the Panja Mahabhutas, and the Shatras, and all these frameworks, which is a good framework, like, which is a good, like, it is the most potent framework of Ayurveda. But itself, if you go into the mental health part of Ayurveda, whether it's Satabajay Chikitza, Devi, Vapashtrajikitsa, et cetera.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, man also has been studied equally in Ayurveda. In fact, if you go and read more into the depths of the Ayurvedic mental frameworks.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It says Pradnea, Prade Jayath Sarva Rogan, in the sense, all the diseases that a person has.
Dr. Karan Mittal: They are because of the crimes of the intellect, in the sense, whenever you do something wrong from your intellectual perspective, whether it's breaking alarm, not following the proper lifestyle, doing anything related to intellect.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And all that shows up in form of diseases in Ayurveda. So when we talk about Sattvaja and Devabypashitza, counseling, etc, becomes a very important part in Ayurveda also, because it tries to kind of rectify those flaws of the intellect, and bring in that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Bring in that lifestyle, bring in that correction through Devar, Vipash, Chikitsa rituals, etc, so that the transmission of how intellect
Dr. Karan Mittal: issues, you know, get converted into rugas. Now, if you see in Ayurveda, like, even in Shastras, there are two words that go together. You might have heard Adi and Vyati.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Yadhi is physical afflictions, Hadi is mental afflictions. So, mental afflictions were studied in Ayurveda, and also they have mapped certain advanced Ayurvedic runs and certain advanced Vedanta grants have mapped how
Dr. Karan Mittal: the Adi, the mental afflictions, turn into vyadis, which we'll be seeing today through the Panj-Posha framework. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: it's not that Ayurveda doesn't talk about mind. In fact, it talks about mind in a more broader sense, more from the perspective of even the habits, the rituals, the lifestyle, the previous lives. Everything put together becomes Ayurveda's psychological framework, and
Dr. Karan Mittal: Also, if you… if you see mind in Ayurveda, it has… it has kind of… like, I think in the day one, we had discussed, like, when Sushut defines, Marshi, Sushut defines a healthy person, he says.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, a person who has a happy mind, Indra, and Atma, that is, he's happy in himself, only that person can be called as healthy. So, Ayurvedic framework of mind is not just
Dr. Karan Mittal: confided to…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Vata Picta Khafa, it goes way beyond Wata Picta Khafa, and also tries to find out, like, if you go to study nutritional Ayurvedic, hereditary, like, the science of high weather and genetics.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It is called as nutrigenomics and all that stuff. We also see why a person is particularly made up of that particular dosha in his life. It is related to some past life issue, which kind of then manifests into that particular dosha in this life, dominant dosha, and then it takes it forward from there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes, so that's… yes, Rojit.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is the Ayurved's Chaturviva, or the four components how Ayurude looks at.
Dr. Karan Mittal: psychological framework.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Bruce, you're on mute.
Govinda Das ji: Basically, there is Sharira, we have discussed this.
Govinda Das ji: I think on the second session, there is body.
Govinda Das ji: there are… there is Sharira, there is Upakarana, there are Indriyas.
Govinda Das ji: And there is mind, and there is Atma. In fact.
Govinda Das ji: We see that even though you may like something physically on your bodily platform, the Indriyas, they resist.
Govinda Das ji: Allergy, we call it as allergy, right, in the modern world.
Govinda Das ji: But the Indriya, sometimes, they independently function of the body.
Govinda Das ji: You may like to eat dhi.
Govinda Das ji: But instantly, you get some reaction because of doing that.
Govinda Das ji: That means what?
Govinda Das ji: there is… There is a craving
Govinda Das ji: But the Indriyas do not… tongue is happy.
Govinda Das ji: But some other organ does not entertain that.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, there is a distinction between body and Indrias. Body is nothing but collection of the senses, but still, they act independent of the body.
Govinda Das ji: And then, of course, there is Manas.
Govinda Das ji: Right? The… the act of… Feeling, experiencing, that means processing.
Govinda Das ji: And then there is Atma.
Govinda Das ji: when we carry, we were discussing about this, there is the Atma.
Govinda Das ji: There is Sharira, and there is Jiva. Jiva is the combination of Mind, body, intelligence.
Govinda Das ji: stole a Sharira and Atma.
Govinda Das ji: And what is Atma? Atma is absence of all Indiriyas, all sharira, all manas, pure, pure consciousness.
Govinda Das ji: Right? So in this 4 thing, when Jiva is integrated in 4 of this.
Govinda Das ji: then that constitutes proper mind, proper body, proper hindriya, and satisfied Atma.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… And the reason, you know, now I spoke about the Pradnaparadha part. Now, we'll see…
Dr. Karan Mittal: how these lenses kind of start integrating with each other, and the best example would be taking Punch Kosha and integrating it with the Ayurvedic part. So, as we know that what we see, what we touch, what we smell, the physical body, is not just… it's just the only one of the bodies, or one of the koshas that… that we know of, but Arishis have spoken of four additional koshas, which are pranamay, Manomay, Vidyan.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and Hananume Kosha, and these five actually form a continuum. It kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: It kind of work in sync in synchronization with each other to lead to either psychological disturbances or physical disturbances, and how it works, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I don't know how many of you know about the punch kosher concept, but just to briefly understand how it is, the under my kosher, the word Anna itself says that, you know, the kosher that is made up of anna, the food we eat, is the anamai Kosha. That means your physical body that you touch, see, smell, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's your under microsha.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Beyond Anamay Kosha is your pranamay Kosha. That is, internal to the Anamay Kosha is your pranme Kosha. Of course, you cannot see the Pranme kosher, it's a subtle kosher, but it's basically the vital energy body of your, of the four… of the five bodies. It's a vital energy body. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: my hand is moving, the energy supplied to the hand to move is provided by Praname Pushin.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The Manomay Kosha is, again, further internal, third in layer, and it is the kosha of desires, so… and emotions. So if I have to move this hand, there has to be a desire. So that arises in Manomay Kosha.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Beyond that, the fourth layer is the Vidyan Maikosha. So now, Vidyan Maikosha is where you feel the need. So, suppose I want to pick up my phone, the need is felt in the Vidyan Maikosha. So, that's your intellect.
Dr. Karan Mittal: where you need analysis, etc. I'm in, you know, the third day's terminology, it's the buddi, where all these analysis is happening of what needs to be done, etc. So that happens in Vidyan Mei Kusha. And finally, it's Ananda Mei Kusha, so as the word suggests, it's about Ananda. But in our functional definition of Anand Mei Kusha, it's the happiness that you feel, okay? Or everything that you do is somewhere or the other for a
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of happiness. So, Anand Mei Kosher is the happiness that is felt after doing
Dr. Karan Mittal: any task. So, just to put it in a different way, so I have to pick up my phone, okay? That need is felt in within my pusher.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then, there is a desire, okay, that my hand has to move to pick up my phone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The pranme Pusha supplies the energy to the hand.
Dr. Karan Mittal: to move the muscles, etc. And finally, the action happens at Handamay Pusha. So that's how these four pushas function in synchronization. And finally, the happiness that I get, because I'm picking up the phone, or talking to a person, or whatever, my need or desire is getting fulfilled, happens in the Hananumai Pusha.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is how these five… we will get into the depth of each kosha, but these… this is the synchronization, or the flow, in which the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: kosher's function, and fault at any of these, you know, processes, or any of these koshas, leads to a fault
Dr. Karan Mittal: In the body, in the mind, in the pranmaikosha, etc, which we'll see, eventually.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah, Annamay Kosher, again, Annamay Kosher.
Govinda Das ji: Okay, it's not simply food.
Govinda Das ji: Anna my Kosher means anything we consume with our senses.
Govinda Das ji: Right? I may eat Sattvik food.
Govinda Das ji: But my music is Tamil.
Govinda Das ji: I'm consuming through my ears.
Govinda Das ji: My music may be very classical, Karnataki Sangit.
Govinda Das ji: But my food may be tamogon.
Govinda Das ji: Right?
Govinda Das ji: And then the sense of touch could be tamu.
Govinda Das ji: So, anything we consume through our senses, the sense of touch, The sense of smell, The sense of hearing.
Govinda Das ji: The sense of taste.
Govinda Das ji: Alright, all this is when integrated, then that anamaya kosher can be defined, this is Rajo, this is sattva, this is Tamo, but generally we define only through food.
Govinda Das ji: And still people ask this question, are they or he was eating Shattvik food, but why they're behaving like this?
Govinda Das ji: Because their food is only sattvik, but other indriyas consuming not so much of Sattva Guda.
Govinda Das ji: Right? And Prada Moyakosh.
Govinda Das ji: Yes, there is water. Water is Annamaya.
Govinda Das ji: But there is a prana.
Govinda Das ji: Right? I'm bathing in Ganga almost every day.
Govinda Das ji: When you bathe in a swimming pool and bathe in a ganga.
Govinda Das ji: You can't even compare only. There is so much of Prana.
Govinda Das ji: There is so much of prana within that water. Therefore, a prana may a kosh…
Govinda Das ji: When you see a rising sun.
Govinda Das ji: When you see the full moon, When you walk.
Govinda Das ji: There is soil, right? There is a soil, but when you walk on a soil which is very, very organic, your prana becomes extremely good.
Govinda Das ji: And based on that prana, then Manome coach is the course of relationship.
Govinda Das ji: Like, one of the first questions, Dr. Karan asked, where is your attention?
Govinda Das ji: Wherever is your attention, that is the place where mind is. So, because monome course is the course of relationship, you may be sitting in Mumbai, you may be sitting in Rishikesh, you may be sitting wherever.
Govinda Das ji: But if your attention goes to Hong Kong, your attention goes to somewhere else. So Manoha Kush is the beginning of becoming all-pervading.
Govinda Das ji: The first two koshas are localized, the third kosher goes beyond the body.
Govinda Das ji: Then comes the Vidney Aname kosh. It's a kosh of identity.
Govinda Das ji: And the fifth kosher is the kosher of bliss, happiness.
Govinda Das ji: service. These are the five foundational idea of 5 koshas.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So these are just a few scriptures where these koshas have been mentioned. It comes in Bhagavatam also, in one of the Kantos. It's in Taitri Upanishad, Thakpa Bodha, Panchatashi. Many scriptures have mentioned this concept. It's just a reference slide of where does the concept come from.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… yes, Rojamin.
Govinda Das ji: Yes. And another interesting part, this puncture kosher…
Govinda Das ji: Generally, what happens, we try to say, oh, now you're too transcend.
Govinda Das ji: You have to overcome the Annamay kosher. Annamay kosher is not important.
Govinda Das ji: there we make a mistake, because Annamaya Kosher doesn't cease to exist till our last breath.
Govinda Das ji: We will drink water, we will eat some food.
Govinda Das ji: So, none of the koshas are disintegrated in next kosher. They continue to exist. As your kosher has a virtuous circle, what happens? The Annamaya Kosha becomes more and more evolved.
Govinda Das ji: And because your anime kosh has become evolved, it does impact your Praname Kush.
Govinda Das ji: If the Praname course is also very evolved, you have a fresh air, fresh water, nice space.
Govinda Das ji: What does it do? That pranamaya Kosha has the power to enhance your monomay Kosha.
Govinda Das ji: Once the monome coach is very, very good, then you interact with people very nicely. There is no provocation, there is no agitation. Rather than reacting, you can respond properly.
Govinda Das ji: So what happened in the Anna Prana Enhanced Manomay Kosha? And you're adding something more to Manomay Kosha.
Govinda Das ji: What does it do? It gives rise to right identity, Vikyan meikosha.
Govinda Das ji: One of the reasons why people call themselves traumatized. Oh, my mother traumatized me, my father traumatized me, because their monomyocia summer got affected. We have so many cases where Karan also deals with.
Govinda Das ji: you know, coming from a spiritual background, eating a Sattvic food, very stable family.
Govinda Das ji: Right? There is no problem of anamaykos, sattvik food, manomekos, pranamekos, very good.
Govinda Das ji: But still, Monomaniacosha's disturbed.
Govinda Das ji: And once the monomericos is disturb.
Govinda Das ji: Then they… rather than finding identity properly, people start canceling the identity.
Govinda Das ji: Canceling their own self, canceling their parent self, canceling their spouse self, canceling their, you know, sibling self.
Govinda Das ji: Because the identity confusion, and once the identity increases, Ran Namayakosha is not possible.
Govinda Das ji: Rather than being grateful, one starts having grudges.
Govinda Das ji: Right? So therefore, only… and in fact, If you carefully analyze.
Govinda Das ji: Our reference point will always come from Annam Mahikosh.
Govinda Das ji: As much as your anime coach is refined, that much your other koshads start becoming more and more, more and more refined, and they continue in an integrated way, in an evolving way, in a virtuous way. It's a virtuous circle.
Govinda Das ji: If that is not virtuous circle, it leads to vicious circle.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Coming to Andamar Kosher, in depth. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, as Peruji said, it's not just the food we consume. Anything that we consume makes up the Annamay Pusha. And… and…
Dr. Karan Mittal: And when we say, talk about tandemai kosher, when you work with a person tandemai kosher, it's also the right kind of food that the person needs, as per his or her prakriti. Now, Prakriti, from Ayurvedic perspective is one thing, but also from a perspective of… I think we discussed one of the days, if a person is already docile, passive, and you tell him to, you know, stop eating spicy food, stop eating
Dr. Karan Mittal: things that agitate him, etc. This person will become further and more docile and more and more passive.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if the person is too hyperactive, and you continue that. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the food, as per one's mental disposition is also equally important. Physical disposition is one thing, mental disposition is another thing. So, accordingly, you need to adjust food.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And similarly, right kind of movement. So, so, right kind of movement in the sense
Dr. Karan Mittal: exercise or whatever the yoga or anything the person is doing. It has to be according to, again, his bodily type. Now, if you have a person who's very hyper, sometimes the therapist or the psychologist suggests, like, that then you need to kind of exhaust the person by exhausting his Anamal Kusha and Pranman Kusha, and then automatically the bodily energies will settle down.
Dr. Karan Mittal: sometimes when, when I work with
Dr. Karan Mittal: people, I asked, like, there's a client of mine, you know, during the childhood or teenagehood, the mother was very obsessive about that female's, bodily appearance.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And used to send her to dietitians, and then, you know, there was a lot of bodily criticism and precautions that were taken, despite the person being good-looking, thin, under, like, normal weight, etc. All this was done. Now, when the client talks to me, the client says that, you know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: She doesn't feel connected with her body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: she doesn't feel a sense of association with the body. And that's where the Anamay Kosha, how you kind of look at your body. Most of the people, teenagers especially, when I work with them, they have so many different, different notions, etc, about the body, because how we condition the body, kala, like, you know, you give these labels at that time. These labels sometimes become so deep that over a period of time, they start developing a dissociation towards
Dr. Karan Mittal: reporting. Now, when this dissociation happens, okay, this person, I'm not grounded enough, you know? If I'm not grounded in my body enough, automatically my thoughts will run at different places, I will overthink, etc, etc. So, one of the core needs, what we'll also see in today's demo is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: start grounding the person into the body. When you are more aware of, especially in the therapeutic, that 1 hour, 2 hour window you have, if the person becomes more aware to the body, automatically that sense of grounding, that sense of… because Anama is made up of earth element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Automatically, that sense of world comes in, grounding, inertia, heaviness, you know, you know that strength, etc. will come in.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Namekosha is also about rounding the person into the body. Right food, right exercise, everyone knows. But therapeutically.
Dr. Karan Mittal: bringing the person from the Vignyanmai to the Anamai during the session automatically gives them, you know, gives them some strength, gives them some slowness, gives them some time to think, etc. So that will kind of start regulating
Dr. Karan Mittal: the thoughts and emotions as well, which we'll see in the demo today. So, either the people, either because of their childhood experiences, they become dissociated from the body, or they become completely attached to the body and over-possessive and over-concerned about the body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… Then this… yes, Ruji, if you would like to add…
Govinda Das ji: Can I speak? Can I speak?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. And the second kosher is… is Praname kosher.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, Pranme kosher… now, there is one Shastriic lineage where we understand koshas from a spiritual perspective, Ayurvedic perspective, etc. And there's also the functional lineage where we try to understand koshas deeper on how they affect the human life. And today, we are going to focus on that part. So, of course, Pranme Kusha is basically the kosher of
Dr. Karan Mittal: Movement, different kind of movement, breath movement.
Dr. Karan Mittal: speaking, moving my hands, every movement that happens is somewhere or the other kind of concerned with the primary pusher. And you will see this in your therapy practice also. Some people will
Dr. Karan Mittal: tend to move very less, and some people will kind of move too much. That's the pranic imbalance. Some people will have a good, controlled breath during the session, and some people will tend to breathe heavily, will tend to breathe quickly. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That also tells you in what state the person is right now with.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sometimes, when the person is breathing too deeply, too heavily, too quickly, the frequency is high.
Dr. Karan Mittal: first few minutes with these kind of clients, I just tell them to kind of regulate the breath, just being more aware of your breath, and then the breath automatically starts regulating itself. Automatically, the ripple effects will flow to under my push also, and monomyusha, and so the client will feel more grounded and in charge of their approaches. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Being aware of these subtle, subtle things during a session also is equally important. If a person is tired, exhausted, or a person is angry or hyperagitated.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the breath will show. You kind of being aware of the chest movements, etc, that will show. And then regulating it starts… that's the first step, in fact, in therapy, that you regulate that breath.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Either through direct command, or by, sometimes, just by speaking slowly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: more with… more gravity in your voice. The client will start replicating.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you are also speaking very quickly and, you know, kind of being hyper, he will also replicate you in that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, all these are subtle cues that you observe and then kind of mimic or mirror in yourself, and then try changing the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also, if you go from a very yogic psychology perspective, breath is something that is under our control also, and beyond our control also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, pranmai Kosha sometimes becomes the… like, now, when we do the demo, we'll see how we can use the movement of breath to work on a particular motion. So, pranmai Kosha is the kosher that links under my and manomai, something that's under our control fully, and something that's beyond our control.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Jocelyn.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah, best part is, about the Scotias.
Govinda Das ji: They don't deal with only the diagnose.
Govinda Das ji: You know, they deal with the solution.
Govinda Das ji: Alright.
Govinda Das ji: So, like Karanji explained, that somebody… Has an issue.
Govinda Das ji: with, active, hyperactive Pranamaya Kosha.
Govinda Das ji: Then, along with breathing control, you also change their food.
Govinda Das ji: Right? You apply some kind of oil also. So, see, the rishis, what they did was…
Govinda Das ji: Every aspect of philosophy Was connected with practical solution also.
Govinda Das ji: There is Brahma Murtha, which say everybody should get during Brahma Murtha.
Govinda Das ji: But the Brahma Murta is also divided into 3 parts.
Govinda Das ji: those who have the hyper Pranhamaya Kosha, it is better that they take some more rest within that one and a half hour period of Brahma Murtha.
Govinda Das ji: The first part of Brahma Murta is good for the kapha people to get up. That means those prana… is very strong.
Govinda Das ji: they should rise, because early hours, the Pitta Prakriti will help them. So even the… even the Muhurtas are divided into three parts.
Govinda Das ji: write your food. If you're too Satvic and you are not activated, then some spicy food is recommended. To such an extent, Wag Bhutta, the great… recently, I saw one, small…
Govinda Das ji: real about Ayurved. The Ayurvedic doctor simply making a statement, Ayurved Ayurveda has given Permission for drinking wine.
Govinda Das ji: Now, when you say like that, what happens? People will start drinking. Already, if people are intoxicated, for them to drink is very bad. So, vague butter gives the timing when to drink, who should be drinking, how many days they should be drinking.
Govinda Das ji: It becomes a medicine.
Govinda Das ji: Most people, because they cannot handle that, the general Ayurvedic doctor, he may say, don't touch it.
Govinda Das ji: Right, so therefore, nothing is poison, and nothing is nectar. It all depends upon what is your kosher, what is your energy, based upon that. Under the guidance of a right healer, one can use even poison as for their progress.
Govinda Das ji: and evolved… Continuity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when we discuss this offline, I usually tell people that, you know, breathe.
Dr. Karan Mittal: quickly, like, take faster breaths, and then try doing a chanting, or try meditating. Or, if you want to shout.
Dr. Karan Mittal: take, you know, slow, deep breaths, and then try shouting. So your breath has to kind of be in sync with your emotions to kind of show up that emotion. If you are breathing slowly, deeply, and in pace, you won't be able to express anger.
Dr. Karan Mittal: At the same time, when you're breathing quickly, and, you know, there's a hyper-breathing, you won't be able to try and meditate, be peaceful. So, if I'm just breathing quickly, quickly, my mind won't be, you know, still or peaceful. So, just by shifting the breath during the first 5 minutes of a session, you try to, you know, if you're going 10 steps without controlling the breath in a session, you'll go 15 steps. Just by shifting the breath to a more
Dr. Karan Mittal: paced and more synchronized thing. That's the power of breathing in sessions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And Manome Kushal, again, I usually ask people, how are you feeling today?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And most of the times, the answers I get is okay, probably happy, you know, those generic, fine. These are the answers that I get. That's okay for giving a reply, but most of the times, even the clients tell you that, you know, I'm feeling okay, fine. At the most, they'll just say, sad, or something of that sort.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But emotional, you know, description of how are you feeling, like, 10 years ago, we were talking about… I think I discussed this, we were talking about emotional intelligence.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And now we are talking about emotional literacy. We kind of identifying what we are exactly feeling is the substratum of manomitosho. We have lost
Dr. Karan Mittal: The ability to feel different, different, different emotions, and then kind of express it out.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the way… the way we are feeling it. So nowadays, we talk about emotional literacy, where we teach how to feel a particular emotion. So, I have few clients, probably 3 to 4 sessions, just go and try to… in trying to dig in, that what exactly are they feeling? Because they have lost touch with their emotion. Most of the time, the answer is, okay, fine.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sad.
Dr. Karan Mittal: frustrated, irritated. But at depth, when we go, you know, deeper to that frustration, irritation, probably comes the jealousy, because I'm not able… I'm not, you know, kind of successful as, like, my brother or my colleague. Or probably comes insecurity, that I'm… I'm… I'm not getting promotion, and people are going ahead of me, etc. So, going into that deeper emotions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sometimes takes time because people are not aware of these deeper emotions. And Manomai Kosher is all about knowing your emotions, being able to express it… express those emotions in the right way, and also expressing your desires in the right way. So Manomay Kosha is also about sense… taking in
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, impressions from the senses, but more important from a functional perspective, it's about knowing your emotions deeply. And we'll see today, probably, in the demo, and you will also get to practice, like, how you kind of try to dig into the core emotion.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How do you feel? Sometimes I just go on asking, so, how do you feel? So, how do you feel? And the person is… there is a time when a person doesn't have words, because they don't know what they are feeling. So, Manomay Kosha is about
Dr. Karan Mittal: Knowing how you feel, and then expressing it the way it is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: He's true.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah, it is so important that Monomeo Kosh also
Govinda Das ji: He's not evolved because there is a concept of respect.
Govinda Das ji: And what is the respect to? Respect every…
Govinda Das ji: Every cultural nuances have their positivity and their negativity.
Govinda Das ji: Right? The problem with respect, I remember one friend was telling, In a very cultured family.
Govinda Das ji: A son was speaking something.
Govinda Das ji: In his own room.
Govinda Das ji: And he was using foul language.
Govinda Das ji: And father came and slapped him.
Govinda Das ji: And he walked away, said, never use this language, and he walked away.
Govinda Das ji: And mother asked him, why you didn't tell that you are… you were actually working on your script on your drama?
Govinda Das ji: The boy was practicing his script for his school function.
Govinda Das ji: And the son couldn't tell his father there is.
Govinda Das ji: Papa, I'm not using forward, this is part of my script.
Govinda Das ji: The father could… the son could not communicate, and father could not ask also.
Govinda Das ji: Right, so therefore, it is extremely important, as Karanji was mentioning.
Govinda Das ji: that a superficial answer, I'm hurt, I'm disappointed, I'm lonely, they're not true answers. As they go deeper, they will understand that there is something greater in that. Therefore, Mano Myikosh.
Govinda Das ji: is giving that space. Today, what has happened?
Govinda Das ji: Today's universe is all about feeling.
Govinda Das ji: And previously, in the cultured setup, it is all about fact.
Govinda Das ji: Fact forced people to hold back their emotions.
Govinda Das ji: And now, it's all about emotions.
Govinda Das ji: Right, either… Overexpressing or not expressing both cause concern to the monomyocortia.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the Vidney and Kosha. And if you see, Manomay and Vidnian koshas are the two koshas that are sometimes so entangled with each other, like we saw in one of the practice sounds yesterday also. We have clarity about
Dr. Karan Mittal: what issues we are having. We have all the knowledge about all the issues that we are having, but we don't have the feeling towards those issues. We don't have the emotions. So, Vivnarme and Manomai, you will see most of the clients are entangled with each other. Either the client will be too emotional.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that's affecting his buddy, the Vidney, or the client will be too vidyan Maik, like, having all the knowledge, all the researches done about the particular issue he or she is having, and… but there's no feeling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So sometimes just shifting the focus to the… the other kosher kind of brings in that insight. Like, in one of the practice rounds I was going, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: the therapist was kind of asking questions, questions, questions. The client knew when it started, the client knew what's happening, how it's happening her. Everything was there. But, but there was no feeling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: how it affected you emotionally, or how it affected your growth, potential, all that stuff. How did it make you feel going up with this emotion? That wasn't there. And as soon as I asked her this question, there was a blankness.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably a pause for a few minutes, because with non-made data is there, the Budri data is completely there, but the feeling is not there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Once the feeling comes in, it's an aha moment, or vice versa.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the person could just be crying, speaking about emotions, I feel, I feel that, I feel that. And we saw in one of the, again, sessions, that if this
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, if this, tendency of yours to help people wasn't there, how would it change?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Shifting the focus to Vidyan Meh, and there was a blank, okay? So, you will see that these two koshas… so, basically, firstly, Vidyan Meh is all about the intellect, the Buddhi part, the discernment part. In fact, when we speak about Pradnea Appra that we started the Ayurveda concept with, it speaks about the and jitti.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The ability to discern, and the ability to make decisions. When these two faculties are compromising, Gudi, these are the sub-faculties, diseases arise.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so Vidyan Meikosha is basically your ability to think, make decisions, everything that your brain does. The intellect part, that's the Vidyan Meikosha. And sometimes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, we have this tendency to over-utilize vign kosher to kind of suppress the other koshas, because as in the part of evolution, or as a part of our scriptural studies, or all that stuff, our Buddhi becomes hypertrophic. We start using Buddhi a lot.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then for every problem, there's a Buddhik hypertrophied explanation.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? The explanation holds true.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? But it kind of snatches you away, or takes you away from actually feeling it, experiencing it in the body, etc, which finally leads to frustration, irritation, and all that stuff. So, everything is happening over here, but there's nothing… there's no connection in the body. There's no connection with it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's what the hypertrophy. That's obsessive rumination about something, or intellectualizing something. Like, I get people that
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's not right to feel emotions. We need to transcend the emotions, okay? And then they have hundreds of slokas of how… how emotions can be probably, pull them back in their spiritual journey, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But… but that's intellectualization. It's not that they're not feeling it. They're trying to run away from feeling it by intellectualizing the whole issue through Shastas. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, having more insight, or having more explanation of the problem is not the solution. Contacting with the monomayor, contacting with the emotion that you are trying to suppress, brings up the solution.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, that would have…
Govinda Das ji: one of the famous philosopher Fedrich Nitze, he knew too many things.
Govinda Das ji: Too fast.
Govinda Das ji: Right? He intellectualized so much.
Govinda Das ji: And because of intellectualizing everything, he's monomy kosher.
Govinda Das ji: His Pranamay Kosha, and his Anna Mahay Kosha was so disrupted, he almost went mad.
Govinda Das ji: And you find this very much. Those who become philosophers, You know, they intellectualize everything.
Govinda Das ji: Right? So what happens? Because their emotions and their prana is not in sync, Either they become self-destructive.
Govinda Das ji: Or they become disruptive in others' life.
Govinda Das ji: And therefore, in the Bhagavad Gita, when Krishna speaks to Arjuna, he explains about Buddha, Bhava, Samantha.
Govinda Das ji: There is Buddhi, and there is Bhava.
Govinda Das ji: And therefore, in a Bharatiya, the Indian knowledge system, as we say, there is a Rasa Shastra. Rasa Shastra is pure description of different emotions.
Govinda Das ji: You know, the five primary emotions of…
Govinda Das ji: the Madhuriya, the Sakya, the… the Watsalia, the Shanta, and Dasya. And then there are 7 primary rasars.
Govinda Das ji: You know, humor, there is viriras, there is Advutras, right?
Govinda Das ji: But these Rasa's, without Nyaya, there is Nyaya, and there is Rasa. Nyay and Rasa, when they're integrated.
Govinda Das ji: What does it do? It enhances our growth.
Govinda Das ji: Therefore, Vigyal can be very dangerous and risky, because now we have…
Govinda Das ji: We have access to everything under the carpet.
Govinda Das ji: And therefore, more access on the knowledge system.
Govinda Das ji: Like, one of the complaints of the doctors, what, the patient comes with ChatGPT.
Govinda Das ji: Giving all the explanation about what medicine the doctor should go give, and what kind of symptoms they have.
Govinda Das ji: Then, rather than adding value to that conversation between doctor and the patient, it simply irritates the doctor, and the patients feel the doctor knows so less.
Govinda Das ji: Information is there.
Govinda Das ji: But the act of conversation is completely lost. So this is not Vikyana, it is simply dumbing us with too much of information.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then the island membership.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Anand Mekusha, as I said, the Shastric perspective is different, but also we have a perspective which is more functional than how we use Anandmeikosha.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, it's… it also talks about that highness, or that kahankar, or that self, you know, association that makes a thing mind, or…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Apart from mine. So, how much of I-ness is associated with a particular issue, makes you feel happy, or any of the negative issues associated with it? I-ness is… the Anandweh kosher is also the difference between self-esteem and self-worth. So… so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Self-esteem is me getting appreciated from people around me, and self-worth is me feeling good about myself. Both together will lead to self-confidence.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But if either of it is imbalanced, okay, if self-esteem is too much, it could lead to superiority complex and all that stuff. If self-esteem is too much, it would lead to a pampered child, etc. So a balance of both.
Dr. Karan Mittal: both the honestness that I have, that self-worth, and also that appreciation coming from outside, will lead to self-confidence. I know parents who have never appreciated the time. I know the parents who have done the opposite.
Dr. Karan Mittal: have too much of appreciation, etc. So, when the self-esteem kind of takes a toll, that is coming from… something coming from outside, it automatically… either the person becomes superior, too pampered, or too weak if the child is not appreciated at all. So… so these people, then, they have a low self-confidence and low self-worth, etc. So, Anandme kosher is how good you feel about your own self. That's basically the
Dr. Karan Mittal: happiness quotient in a very functional sense. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I usually ask people, when was the last time you felt happy? When we're doing this offline, it's very interesting to see how much a person knows about the happiness they have felt. When was the last time you felt happy?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Which was the memory that made you feel happy? What is the thing that makes you feel happy? I think I told you in the first session, I had a client who took so many sessions just to make a list of 3 or 4 things that makes her feel happy. So, on how much, on a daily basis, you feel happy is basically your Anand Mai Koshai Nash.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, you'll come, you'll see people, you know, who, who, who have,
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of have everything, all the other koshas are there in place, but there's a sense of lack of happiness. And these are people who have, you know, are very successful, etc, but they don't lack… they lack meaning in their life, they lack happiness in their life. That's Anandme Kosha, I feel.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, working and bringing in tools and different engagements to kind of bring in that happiness in their life on a day-to-day basis, week-to-week basis, month-to-month basis, and increasing intensity, starts making them, you know, feel more positive, and half of your things are taken care of. Because if you see from neurology also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: All the negative hormones and chemicals are running in the body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But there is nothing that makes a person feel happy. So bringing in happiness through different tools initially starts opening up that part of the brain, and then over a period of time, this starts taking over the negative.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's Anand, my question. Yes, Fusion.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah, the distinction between Manomay Kosha and Anand Mai Kosher, you may get confused.
Govinda Das ji: In Monomai Kosha, we derive Satisfaction from relationships.
Govinda Das ji: Because mind is not… One point, it goes everywhere.
Govinda Das ji: But Anand Namay Kosha… Anand Mikosha is basically… Finding satisfaction within oneself only.
Govinda Das ji: Therefore, Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita, he explains, That one was equipoised.
Govinda Das ji: Right? One who is able to be experienced equipoised. Now, what is equipoised in our level?
Govinda Das ji: Equipoisements… When there is victory, you do not celebrate your victory more than it deserves.
Govinda Das ji: Right? You can't avoid celebration.
Govinda Das ji: Equipoise doesn't mean that there are no emotions.
Govinda Das ji: But equipoise means when you have a celebration.
Govinda Das ji: Which is meant to be for 10 minutes, 20 minutes, 30 minutes. Like, when you take a wicket, when you're playing a cricket match.
Govinda Das ji: Right? When you see your team is…
Govinda Das ji: Getting overhand against other teams, it is a time for celebration.
Govinda Das ji: But the match is not over.
Govinda Das ji: Even if the match is over, the next match is there.
Govinda Das ji: So, when somebody is able to experience equipoisonous.
Govinda Das ji: Do not suffer more than it deserves.
Govinda Das ji: do not enjoy more than it deserves, then one actually is situated in Parmatma. That is what Krishna speaks to Arjuna.
Govinda Das ji: Right? Now, Stittapragnya is not freedom from emotion. Stittapragnya is experiencing coherent emotions.
Govinda Das ji: Imagine people share their story 20 years ago, what happened to them, repeatedly. What they're doing? They're watering
Govinda Das ji: To that pay, and keeping that payment alive.
Govinda Das ji: So they will not experience self-satisfaction.
Govinda Das ji: Right? So therefore, the therapeutical Anandamay Kosha is learning the art of experiencing self-satisfaction. That does not mean there is no pain.
Govinda Das ji: That does not mean there is no happiness, but happiness and distress have… proper…
Govinda Das ji: response, not more, not less, such person become, certainly, Sitaparagya, and he already experiences Paramatma. That is Ananda Kosha in a clinical perspective.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And probably the reason… one of the reasons we…
Dr. Karan Mittal: dealt with koshas a bit quickly is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: This is the main crux of working with quotients.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, koshas are not, like, individual entities and working independently. They're interdependent, and these are the three movements that can happen in a kosher.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Lateral interference, we just saw. Lateral interference is one Portia affecting the next push. So we saw that with Manumai and Vignme are entangled with each other. And sometimes the therapy is, or in your counseling session, you just need to shift the focus, either from Vignhyanmai to Manumai, or Manumai to Vignhyaymay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Or, if the person is angry and has come, you know, charging in your session, paranormal and monoma is over here. So, just shifting the balance of the paranormal, that is, regulating the breath, will start affecting the monoma. So, this is lateral interference, and in one client, you'll see
Dr. Karan Mittal: One of it being dominant always, okay? That's how it is. That's the shift of the balance, to other side, and that's why
Dr. Karan Mittal: If… if Vignanma is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably, you know, heavy, then we give them exercises of monomize. Monomai is heavy, we tell them to journal it, to things of Vidnamaya, vice versa. So, this keeps on happening, lateral interference. Most importantly, what comes from our scriptural,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Scriptural intelligence is the downward and upward probation. So I'll give you an example of how it happens.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, what is downward propagation or upward propagation? You might, both are actually same, it's just the direction changes. So supposedly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'm working in some corporate, and I'm a CEO or something of that sort.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I am under high stress. There are too many things that run in my mind, there's too much of task to be done, so my Buddhi, or my Vidan, my kosher is completely congested. Okay, too many things are always on my plate. So I'm working more than necessary in my intellectual focus.
Dr. Karan Mittal: This intellectual capacity, over a period of time, will start affecting the monomipusha, will lead to, you know, kind of frustration, irritation, anger, different people, different, different emotions will come up in Manomipusha.
Dr. Karan Mittal: When this frustration, irritation, anger stays there for a very long period of time, it will start imbalancing the nadis.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, nadis are basically a part of the prana person. Okay, nadis is basically movement of energy into different, different… moment of prana into different, different parts, so the nadis will start getting imbalanced.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this imbalance of Nadi usually happens around, depending on which emotion it is, it usually happens around… somewhere around the abdominal area, and then slowly, this will convert into under my pressure, leading to issues like acidity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: IBS, chronic indigestion, so it will start showing up in your digestive system.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is the scriptural intelligence that these koshas are not independent from each other. They pass. Depending upon the time, they will pass their effect to the surrounding koshas. And the surrounding koshas, then further, further, further, further, it will keep on going.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? So, that's how it happens. The person who has… and vice versa is also what happens. If a person who has chronic… has eaten something spicy, etc, there will be burning sensation in the stomach. Burning sensation in the stomach will make the person restless. That restlessness might come out as irritation, frustration, anger in… to the person opposite to you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, from the symptom of undermine, then brand my restlessness, then monomai, that is probably, anger, irritation, frustration, and then the person might speak, or kind of, you know, pick up a fight with the opposite person, the victim light.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So these POSHAs don't work independently, they are interdependent, and you can stop this cycle anywhere.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, from Vidnamay to Manomay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: different, different therapies work, right? As I said, journaling, talking, you know, different, different therapies kind of work here, Vignan Mae Manomay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Manomay, praname…
Dr. Karan Mittal: pranik healing, Reiki, all these things work, where we kind of start changing the Pranamay Kusha. And then the undermay Kusha, your medical systems work, where I look at, whether it's modern medicine, Ayurveda, homeopathy, it works on the Annamay kosher. So all your
Dr. Karan Mittal: systems of healing, well-being, etc. Somewhere or the other, break this cycle.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, and what is the best form of breaking? You work on the Kanya Paran, that is the Buddhi, or whatever is happening at the… with Nyan mepusha. You break that, automatically the whole cycle collapses.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's basically understanding how you work with… how you work with the five pushas in therapeutic context, and we'll see a demo now. So… so that's upward and downward propagation, and we also saw the lateral interference. So, I will need a volunteer, okay? We'll do a bigger demo today.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then also a bigger practice sound, so that you can do this full peeling thing. I call this as the peeling of the issue, and you can kind of bring that issue right up to the undermay Posha, by this peeling technique. So I will need someone to volunteer for today's demo.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Anyone?
Suraj Racha: I can…
Dr. Karan Mittal: when we met.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Suraj G. Yes, Ruji, can you, switch on your video if…
Suraj Racha: Miss…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I'll be explaining all along. Suraji, is it okay with you? So that… so that we have a good… like, whatever is applicable, just explain it to her. Yes. So, Suraji, would you like to take up something very short and superficial as an issue? Like, could you describe it very… it could also be a case, like, something you create, but…
Dr. Karan Mittal: A more experiential one would be beneficial.
Suraj Racha: Sure, sure. So, one of the issues is, regarding the lifestyle, basically.
Suraj Racha: I tried to sort things out as much as possible, so as to maintain a balance, but somehow, because of the work or many unknown factors, especially the scheduling part.
Suraj Racha: goes for a toss. Because of that, many other aspects are also affected, like, my productivity, or
Suraj Racha: how I deal with others, so some relations to that as well.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So he has, in fact, given a good, you know, 4 important words.
Dr. Karan Mittal: lifestyle, scheduling, productivity, and relationship with others. He has already come to Manomay, relationships with others. Okay? Now, there are two ways. I can directly ask him, how does it feel when you have too many things on your plate? That's one way of
Dr. Karan Mittal: going, and then you might say a few emotions, etc, and then I can heal it down. But I'll take the more complex route.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Wow.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Suraj, you said that there are scheduling, you know, issues, like, lifestyle issues and something related to time schedules, probably, something related to that. Okay, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Why do you probably take so many things, or what makes you take up so many things? Like, is it… is it a compulsion, like, you have been told to take it up, or it's your own need? How does it…
Dr. Karan Mittal: How does suit?
Suraj Racha: Yes, yes. So, I mean, I'm not unhappy or forcefully taking it up, like, it's more because of the supportive behavior which is there. So, it, it is also coming that,
Suraj Racha: Things are for a better purpose, like.
Suraj Racha: I can contribute more through that. At the same time, it also kind of satisfies the sportive nature which is there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so again, a year two was contribution, and that's quoted nature.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How does it feel to be contributing in sport diffs?
Suraj Racha: It really feels good, like, a big chunk of myself is satisfied with it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… So, if this voting and this contribution wasn't there, how would that feel?
Suraj Racha: Then it would be really frustrating, like, very, depressive.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Beer.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, you said frustrating and depressive. So, again, Prabhali, I'll ask you, was there a time where you felt this frustration and depression of not contributing?
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'm going deep, you can stop me anywhere, okay? It's not that you need to run this through.
Suraj Racha: Maybe, yes, some couple of years ago, where I wanted to bring out certain things, but somehow they were not coming out in picture, so that was a kind of frustrating time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this frustration was, like, Your own frustration, or it was, like, imposed frustration?
Suraj Racha: What does it mean?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, you felt this frustration that you were not able to do things, or it was, like, a societal frustration, or someone told you something.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, we don't be so direct of someone to do something, but just for today's sake, I'm just taking that one.
Suraj Racha: Largely for myself only, you know, when they… Outside things were quite normal.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If I ask you, Where do you feel this frustration in your body?
Suraj Racha: Registration info.
Suraj Racha: mostly… You mean a physical part? Like, a bodily part?
Dr. Karan Mittal: but…
Govinda Das ji: Yes.
Suraj Racha: It's difficult to say, maybe in the heart region.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I always notice the facial expressions. So, so, the client is smiling right now when he says the heart key. Okay, so something is, you know, there's an unnatural movement happening, there's unnatural praname movement happening.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Primary is basically moon.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so frustration is not related to me. So I'm seeing the client's mind, so I'll now dig it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, what exactly is happening? So, maybe just for a minute, and again, I'm again telling you, if you want to stop anytime, just feel free to stop. We just close your eyes, yeah.
Suraj Racha: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe we could go into that memory, where a few years ago, you said.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How do you see yourselves, maybe?
Suraj Racha: You want me to say?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, how do you see yourself in that memory of yours, where you were trying things, but not… things were not working out?
Suraj Racha: Meh… It was quite…
Suraj Racha: frustrating. I mean, I didn't lose the enthusiasm, but at the same time, a little disappointing.
Suraj Racha: Yes, I mean, these two were prominent things. The enthusiasm was not lost, but at the same time, it was… it's more like a sport only, like, for example, if we are playing football, then it's already 45 minutes in, but there's still… I'm not able to put a goal in. So, more like that kind of feeling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just keep your eyes closed for… yeah, this is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So you are into a football game.
Suraj Racha: But at the same time, one more prominent thing there was, nothing was much on stake. Like, I mean, I'm still into my studies, there was not a financial burden, so even a loss was not coming at a high stake.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Something is at stake right now.
Suraj Racha: At that time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And today, as of today, what's at stake?
Suraj Racha: As of today.
Suraj Racha: Slightly, it has come into stake, because what I'm doing may also shape my future. Like, it may directly or indirectly be related to my own financials, or the social circle. So, the stakes have increased.
Suraj Racha: Significantly, if not with the highest texture.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if I may change the line of questioning a bit.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when there are too many things to schedule, and if you're not able to schedule things well, how do you feel? Or you are not productive enough?
Suraj Racha: Actually, I faced a lot of burden as well.
Suraj Racha: In the face of that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Lot of burden has, sorry.
Suraj Racha: If, for example, there was…
Suraj Racha: 10 things to come… 10 meetings in the day, but only 7 of them happened, then it was like, okay, no issues, I'll… it's better only. Like, a part of my is… mine also knows that if I schedule the next 3 on the next day, then nothing much is going to lose. It's alright.
Suraj Racha: But at the same time, some impetus, some, like, unnatural impetus is there, which makes me push, like, okay, I can still squeeze in the other three. So when, the schedule mismanagement happens, I'm kind of okay convincing myself, okay, this can…
Suraj Racha: Like, it… I take it as a landing page, okay?
Suraj Racha: It can be scheduled on the next day, then things are still moving around.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, again, there's a big Yanme description.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I asked, how do you feed?
Suraj Racha: So there's not much feeling associated with, disrupted scheduling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And what about when it affects your productivity and your relations?
Suraj Racha: Oh my god.
Suraj Racha: I mean, relations, it… it does not affect
Suraj Racha: a relation so directly, but more like making out time, so time can become an issue.
Suraj Racha: Because any healthy relation is directly related to how much time we are… time or mental space we are able to put in. So I was coming from that end when I say relations.
Suraj Racha: And how it affects… So what was the question, Suri?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, how does it feel when it starts affecting your productivity and your relationships?
Suraj Racha: Again, it feels a little bit frustrating, in the sense
Suraj Racha: There can be… there could have been more stability derived from being more productive, or being more, healthy, being more mentally available as relations, but that, stability grounding may be missed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And can you feel that frustration right now in your body?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe if you would go to a memory first. Maybe close your eyes just, just… maybe just a minute more, I'll take yours. Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So.
Suraj Racha: What do you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: IBM, we've Yup.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The frustration that Kind of comes up when productivity and relationships are kind of, you know, hampered.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe we could take up one recent memory. I don't need the memory, but something that has happened in recent few days.
Suraj Racha: I feel bad, because, like… Like, I can narrate one incident also.
Suraj Racha: I mean, someone was trying to talk to me and express themselves, but I was… it's not more about the physical time, but I was mentally so occupied with some things that… I was doing a… yes, yes, yes, from outside, but I knew that internally… internally, I'm not available for the other persons, so…
Suraj Racha: That really felt bad, Key. Someone had come with good…
Suraj Racha: faith, but I was not really mentally available for them, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so you spoke about frustration, right? Were you able to feel it in your body?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just for the demo, because I can go to another route of questioning, but for the demo, are you able to feel that frustration?
Suraj Racha: Kind of, not in the exact same intensity.
Suraj Racha: Glimpses of it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Any part of the body where you can locate it?
Suraj Racha: I gave my beat.
Suraj Racha: I don't know, near the heart region already, but, like, can point out something about…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay. Now, okay, Suraji, thank you. So, usually what I tell the client after this is, I tell them to keep their hand over here, and try to breathe in, and try to release the frustration through your mouth outside. That's how we kind of discharge the emotion.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… Just to explain, Vidyanne McClarity was there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Frustration has been the root cause of emotion, okay? And that's somewhere located here in the anomatraha. Now, this comes from somatic psychotherapy, that somatic psychotherapies are based on this model, where from the thoughts you go to the emotions, restlessness in the body, and where you store that emotion in the body. Once the location is diagnosed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then we tell the person to breathe in using pranamaya power, breathe in, dilute the emotion, breathe out.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, I can give a case conceptualization of what's happening, but it wouldn't be right to do it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Rooja, would you like to add something?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Hmm.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we… yes, yes, Bush.
Govinda Das ji: I think, can you give more analysis about this?
Govinda Das ji: This part of interaction between you and him.
Govinda Das ji: Or clarity?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, I can.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I'm just taking the consent from Suraji, like, and implying that consent is there. So, see, the frustration has been a root cause even a few years ago, and today also, whatever is taking up is leading to frustration. Now, the next step, I would have asked that
Dr. Karan Mittal: what will happen if you stop taking so many things on your plate, or you stop playing it like a sport? You might come up with a statement, okay? Maybe, if you want to show addict an ad, that you… there could be somewhere a deeper
Dr. Karan Mittal: self-worth association with taking up too many things on the plate, okay? There was a time when I took up things that didn't work out, so I will take so many things up right now on my plate that at least few will work out, or at least I'll, you know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I think he said, many things are at stake. I'm contributing, I'm… I'm doing a better… it's a better purpose. So… so you kind of take up larger goals, so that… that self-worth gets driven. That's… that's my concept in the 5 minutes of what I understood.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So we started with…
Dr. Karan Mittal: lifestyle scheduling, so these… this was he describing his Vidnan Maya, Gudi speaking, that lifestyle is an issue, scheduling is an issue, productivity is an issue, relationship is an issue. So, he had understood his problem. Then I asked him how did he feel?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So he said it feels frustrating. Like, there were two lines of, questioning. One is, how does it feel when you're not able to schedule things well and it affects productivity? So it's frustrating and depressing. I took the different route, that was there a time when you could… when, you know, you took up things and things were not working, etc? That also led to frustration.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I came to Manumai, okay? Then, then, from Manumai, I asked him.
Dr. Karan Mittal: where are you feeling it in your body, okay? So… so he said somewhere around the chest area, so that's locating that emotion to undermine.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then from under May, I would have told him to keep one of his hands over there, and use the power of pranme, that is, breathing in slowly, breathing out through your mouth, and kind of diluting, or kind of releasing that emotion out, which itself leads to some amount of somatic psychotherapy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I think that's the basic explanation of what I did in this session. So, basically, when you practice, the client will speak his issue, try to find out how much is he feeling, what is he feeling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And it might require some time. Frustration might go into irritation and sadness. I didn't go into that part.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then finally, try to locate that emotion in the body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Keep up on.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Breathe in, breathe out. Okay? That's the practice.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Does that make sense, Roshi?
Govinda Das ji: Hmm.
Govinda Das ji: So, if somebody is not like Suraj.
Govinda Das ji: You know, he might express more emotion than intellectualization, right?
Govinda Das ji: Then the solution is different for the same problem.
Govinda Das ji: But seen from a… somebody will see more from an intellectual perspective, more will see from a bodily perspective.
Govinda Das ji: Or, because they behaved with me, you know, I started eating too much, like, therefore I put on my weight, you know, and still I'm not, happy with that. So some people are affected physically, some people are affected emotionally, mentally, and some people are…
Govinda Das ji: you know, they are intellectualizing it, alright? That's what I understand. And based upon what they're intellectualizing, or expressing emotions, or expressing on their bodily
Govinda Das ji: Impact, accordingly, the healer or a therapist.
Govinda Das ji: Papest?
Govinda Das ji: will, you know, deal with their kosher, whether it is Anamay, Praname, Anomai, Vickyame, or Annai Kosh, correct?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's… that's what, yeah, shift the focus from the kosha…
Govinda Das ji: Anybody has question on this specific?
Govinda Das ji: Anybody has question on this exercise? The other question we'll take later.
DhyanShala: Yes, yes, I have a question. Yeah.
DhyanShala: Dr. Mittal, in this psychosomatic therapy, what we have done right now, what I have seen, is that there may be some, like, first, we are,
DhyanShala: Tapping manome, then we are trying to get the location of the body where it is But…
DhyanShala: And then we're trying to release the frustration from that body part. So, there may be the possibility that this all is occurring because of past some scar also.
DhyanShala: Let's… The person who's telling.
DhyanShala: There may be confusion in his mind, or her mind, that it may be some other body part as well.
DhyanShala: But what he is telling us, in this particular case, Suraji has told that it may be…
DhyanShala: I think I have felt this in my heart.
DhyanShala: He was not sure.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sure. Sue? Hmm.
DhyanShala: And apart from this body, my previous question was that it may be this all
DhyanShala: pain of thought, maybe because of past some scar also. So, can we heal that also through this, Punch Kosh therapy system?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, as I said, you know, it's where you break the cycle. So, yes, you can do that. It's like…
Dr. Karan Mittal: I think in one of the sessions I had spoken. Do we need to open the past life Pandora's box every time? Not needed. If…
Dr. Karan Mittal: working on the symptoms, or working on this life, sanskaras and vasanas itself gives you the result, then it's done. So where you break the cycle, this is a bigger loop, rather than working on the smaller loops of this life. So you don't need to, you know, always go to the bigger loop.
Dr. Karan Mittal: these smaller loops also, you can arrest the cycle any, right? So, yes, with Panchosyamandra, you can work on the symptoms of the past life, since Karabasmas.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And secondly, the question that you said, that the client might be confused, etc, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In therapy, you work with the client's narrative.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Like, that's a room. You…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you cannot start the session by doubting what the client is saying. So, one or two sessions, we work around the narrative. And… and when you start working around the narrative.
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably in one or two sessions, if the client is really confused and doesn't know what he or she is talking, experiencing, etc, you get an idea, because therapy will not go anywhere. There would be change of emotions. Like, he kept to the word frustration and frustration, so I knew that that's the emotion, okay? But if at one point you had said frustration, sometimes anger, sometimes sadness, or the emotions kept shifting, the body space kept shifting.
Dr. Karan Mittal: then we know that the client doesn't know what's happening with him or where. So that time you need some more psychoeducation, explain that. I usually tell my clients that when I'm angry, I feel it in my chest, but when I'm frustrated, this part of the head becomes shady. So different emotions have different… so that's called as psychoeducation.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And, I think… yeah, I'm…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Usually, if I had more time, I would have told Suresh to kind of visualize himself in that one situation, where he made that scheduling error, or there was too much to schedule, and he was not able to match it, and then probably repeat to himself that I'm feeling frustrated.
Dr. Karan Mittal: this repetition of the sentence itself would have, you know, kind of deepened the charges in the chest, and then I would have localized it, okay? If you're still feeling it in the chest, it is the chest.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So these are the answers to your three questions. So sometimes repeating that statement just for the sake of therapy, I'm angry, I'm frustrated, I'm sad, helps localize the emotion where exactly it is. Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Any other questions, or should we break out into rooms?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I would say, take the role of 15 minutes of therapist, 15 minutes of client, two people only, not an observer, because we don't have that much time. I'll try to put two… if you have three, only one group might have 3, then 10-10 minutes each, and try to come to the Annamay Kusha. If you are not able to do that part, that's fine, but Vidyanmai, Manomai.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And Anna May, at least 3 koshas, try to ask questions and change the koshas. Even if you're not able to go into that hierarchy, try changing the kosher from Vidnamay to maybe Manamai, from Manamai to Vidnamay to Annamay. Just keep on…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, playing around with… not playing, but just try experimenting with the oceans. Yeah.
Govinda Das ji: Can you give, four high steps where they can… what they're supposed to do?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so you ask the client to take up any simple issue, not something very complex that doesn't have too much of description. Let them describe the issue, try to understand it in a few minutes, then try to ask how do they feel about the issue. They might give you one feeling, or again, they might, you know, kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: run around the bush and not describe your feeling. Try to ground them to the emotion.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then once they tell you, okay, I'm feeling frustrated, is there any other emotion that's there? They're probably angry, frustrated. What's more dominant, anger or frustration? Frustration?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, feel that frustration in your body, close your eyes, go to that memory, feel that frustration, and see which part of your body are you feeling that frustration. Only this much, for now. If you're able to achieve the part, keep your palm.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Breathe in, in that part, and breathe out that emission out.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Simple.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Family.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just give me a moment.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so join the breakout rooms, please.
Suraj Racha: 10G, which room to join, it's not showing the number is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Which is Surajiha, since you were co-host, you were not added, I'll add you to some room, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Renuka Bhuta: Prabhujay, kardan Prabhujay, I have a question.
Renuka Bhuta: Because, I'm not able to feel the, feel the frustration, or whatever it is, in my body part. How do I understand which part of the body, like, how do I connect to that?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Boop.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The ideal way would be to get to a memory that has strongest frustration.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then visualize yourself there, okay? And then probably say those sentences that I'm frustrated, and then again, check. Sometimes it takes time for the body to open its subtle senses, so it's not… it takes a few sessions, sometimes one or two sessions, to make the client aware.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of how to feel it in the body. So maybe go to a memory that's strongest for you about frustration, and then see how Renuka felt in that memory in the body at that day.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That will give you an insight.
Renuka Bhuta: But is it necessary to have that, fee, or it's, not so much necessary?
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you work from the Punch Kosha angle, definitely it's necessary, but different therapies have other ways around them, but since we are seeing the Punch Kosha model, yes, it's necessary.
Renuka Bhuta: And it, helps to understand or identify.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Both… no, no. Understand, identify is the preliminary part. Once the body… you know which part of the body you felt it, it helps you regulate that intention. There's a technique that comes in Panchakosha, where we regulate that emotion. Basically, it increases your threshold to that particular intention.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, suppose I'm feeling it in my chest.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is a 5-liter container, and I have 6 liters of angle over here. It will overflow, and when it overflows, it comes out in the form of words, fitting, etc, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But once you are more aware of your torso, Dharnamusha's torso, this 5L container becomes 10L, so your body is able to contain that anger in a better way.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But that's a more advanced technique.
Renuka Bhuta: How it helps the therapist, therapy, the person who is taking the session, to control their emotions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Control, maintain, dilute, different, different words for different, different.
Renuka Bhuta: Alright, thank you.
Suraj Racha: Here we go.
Suraj Racha: Backing us from the London…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, how was it for all of you?
Dr. Karan Mittal: If one or two of you could share your experiences before we get into questions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Defined.
Suraj Racha: Skin name?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Suraji, please.
Suraj Racha: And Cilandro, did you have your concerns for bringing in some parts of our discussion?
Alessandro Chávez: Yep.
Suraj Racha: So, yeah, I could actually diagnose a lot of it.
Suraj Racha: because it's a milder version, I can, like, bring in some parts, so…
Suraj Racha: The manomic coach was having, maybe, a lot of problems in the sense, they weren't…
Suraj Racha: Do not want to hurt the other person.
Suraj Racha: And the Vigyanme push was quite clear that
Suraj Racha: The other person is wrong, or there's no sound reason in it, but the Manong coach was saying that
Suraj Racha: We… it had a face of its own, saying that I have to be respectful, or I do not have to disagree.
Suraj Racha: At the same time, Just a second, I'm pulling out my notes.
Suraj Racha: And the feelings which were coming out is being stressed about the situation, feeling encapsulated or irritated. Irritated is, again, irritated slightly to pranme Push, but that was not prominent.
Suraj Racha: Mostly, like, being…
Suraj Racha: The, like, the stress feeling was coming up, and it actually directly connected to the Ananda push also, because…
Suraj Racha: there's an I-ness associated, because when the person is able to express themselves, they are feeling themselves that, okay, I am myself, I'm my own self, and that brings to joy, and feeling relaxed, feeling happy. At the same time, when they were not able to express themselves, then
Suraj Racha: the INS was missing, like, where do I belong, or I do not even belong to this particular conversation.
Suraj Racha: And finally, it was felt in the throat and chest reason as prominent.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Well done.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I think proper, you know, POSHA, POSHA diagnosis. Any difficulties, any doubts about the technique?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Any specific difficulties you encounter? Yeah.
Alessandro Chávez: Yeah, I think for me, during the session.
Alessandro Chávez: when she… when I asked multiple times, and we were going through the same… at that point, conclusion on restlessness and, you know, certain feelings that she was feeling.
Alessandro Chávez: I… I was not able to go deeper, because I wasn't sure if there was anything else to get from… from these feelings. So, how were you able to know that there was more?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, of course, it will come with…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you doing a few more sessions, this is the first time you're diving into it. And of course, when I send the handout, I would give you, like, if I don't know whether you saw the Guna Drill handout, but it had a few questions that you can ask the client to ship the goodness. I'd given at least 15 to 20 questions for you to practice with different, different people, but…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Also, what told me that I have to go deeper is the word restlessness is not an emotion.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's a state of brain, or it's a state of the physical body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I… I can say I feel restless, but it's not the one of my question. You need to know the primary emotions, so… so, probably, I'll share that chart also in the handout. There's a wheel of emotions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: which has all those words that are related to emotions. So, happiness, joy, surprise, excitement, jealousy, irritation, anger, frustration. So, these are emotions. I can feel that. Restlessness is a state of being, it's a condition. So, I knew that this is probably superficial, and also, with experience, you'll come to know that
Dr. Karan Mittal: If the client is looping into the same thing again and again, again and again, you'll know that you can go… you have to go deeper.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the best way over here is, if you don't know, ask.
Dr. Karan Mittal: just try making a question with the word restless, and see if you get something substantial coming up. Like, in her case, we got a few words, I have not written down, but that already, you know, it took the whole session a bit more.
Dr. Karan Mittal: depot. So, if you're getting somewhere by asking questions, just keep on asking ourselves.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That comes with experience, the truth. It's just, you do it with 2-3 more clients, you'll get the hang of it.
Govinda Das ji: Will you give the… will you give some, more specific chart, how far… how they can do it?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Ruji, handout. Of course, this also has… the PPT also, which I'll share, will have something, but also I'll give a few questions for every OSHA in the handout. Like, the Western model? Yes, Ruji, sorry.
Govinda Das ji: what I noticed is, when the conversation happens.
Govinda Das ji: You know, when somebody's sharing their problem.
Govinda Das ji: It becomes a story, rather than…
Govinda Das ji: You know, dealing with the feelings. And once they express the feeling, the other party are not equipped, as you said, they're doing it first time. You know, they are in the mode of giving solutions rather than actually dealing with what feeling they're going through. I think this requires little tools and practice also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: See, if you go to any Western psychological technique.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the therapy, they'll teach you… they'll give you the tools first, and then they'll push you in the swimming pool. But in the Indian way, we experience what's it first, and then probably then we enhance it with the tools so that you know where you are lying. So, I purposefully, in the handout, I give more extra details of how to do it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Also, therapy… these breakout rooms are not about you becoming the gani and teaching someone something. It's about you experiencing clienthood and therapisthood, and the opposite person experiencing the same.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So it's very important to get out of that
Dr. Karan Mittal: need to, I think, as Peruji said, give solutions. We tell the client to come up with solutions, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, sir, you have your hands up, and then we can take up the remaining portion and take up the, yeah.
Suraj Racha: So, one doubt was here in this case, when, asylum Judi was mentioning, stress, so…
Suraj Racha: the description was not matching the feeling. For example, I felt there were tinges of anger, rather than being pissed. So, in such a situation, like, I was quite convinced it has tinges of anger. So, should we try to put words in the client's mouth, or should we let them only come up with it?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Depends on the session. The first session, you cannot do that. It will… like, that's what. It will come slowly as you keep on doing it. It will impact the RAPO building of the client. First session, you do whatever is available to it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then, probably in the second session, you can say, but is there a tinge of anger to it, or is there a feeling of jealousy to it, or the insecurity to it? And once they've processed that stress.
Dr. Karan Mittal: in the session by that body and all that stuff, they'll be better… in a better position to go to anger and insecurity and whatever else comes up. So we don't dig in too much.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But at the same time, we also kind of maneuver as per how much the client is ready to accept. Because sometimes these stronger words, anger, jealousy, etc, also kind of impact the client's self-concept, you know? That I can feel angry for such a petty thing, or something like that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, you back out when you feel that you're going too deep in the first or second session, and then accordingly, from client to client, it refers. So, we don't put the but words in the first session at least.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Hmm.
Suraj Racha: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so if there are no more questions, we'll just get to the PPT and complete.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is about, I think, when one's… one… one fociab becomes overactive compared to other foci, these are the symptoms that develop.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, as I said, when the Vidhyunma is too active, especially, you'll see with highly educated, highly functional clients, high positions in life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, not too much of achievement, etc. Too much of intellectualization is already there, because that's their day-to-day work. So in these clients, grounding the session to emotions becomes very important. Otherwise, they know everything.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And they are probably better… better at you. And also, in clients who have very high IQ compared to you, okay, that also becomes a problem. They are able to kind of intellectualize everything to you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And and you don't have, you know, kind of contradictory points to that intellectualization. So grounding the session to Manomaya or Anna May becomes very important.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also, somatization is when the body starts showing up, when you're not aware of the body at all.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Different aches and pains, undiagnosed aches and pains, undiagnosed diseases, chronic fatigue and unexplained fatigue. All these now, even the modern medicine has started kind of propounding that this is more of an, more of a psychosomatic issue. So when you have clients with these symptoms, it's their body speaking up because their emotions have not spoken up for years, are probably decades.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So slowly, Right, now we went from Vidnanoi to…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably Annamay. There's also a technique from going for… going from Annamay to Vidyan Mai Anamay, and all that. So, top-down technique and bottom-up technique. So that bottom-up technique usually we use. And spiritual bypass, I think.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We all know that, you know, things virtual, you know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Shastras and spiritual injunctions to kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: neutralize, or to kind of justify our belief systems, our emotions, the way we behave, etc. That's the spiritual purpose. Very common, commonly seen, especially in spiritual aspirants. So, sometimes I tell the clients.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In my session, don't bring God, don't bring any scripture, don't bring Shiva, don't bring Krishna, don't bring Vishnu. I don't want to hear any of these same things in the session.
Dr. Karan Mittal: speak about Earth, speak about family, speak about emotions. I don't want to hear any of these things. That's sometimes shocking to the client. They might feel we are atheist, etc, etc, but that's needed because everything has a diversion, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: when we do hypnosis for certain clients, some clients see Krishna, Shiva, Vishnu in the hypnosis, and I tell them to send Krishna, Shiva, Vishnu away, because that's not the place where we have to be, okay? You're going into your subconscious mind, going into a childhood, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: how… what are they doing there? So it's like a spiritual bypass, that they are there, and then everything can be put on them without taking the onus of the traumas, the responsibilities, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Forgiveness sometimes go way beyond what is needed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? They want to forgive everyone, but deep down, they're carrying that hatred, jealousy, anger, etc. So, no, like, you'll understand how to kind of work with these things, but, forgiveness, etc, sometimes I avoid taking… bringing these noble emotions and noble concepts from the session, because it's very easy for the clients to bypass
Dr. Karan Mittal: What they are suffering, feeling, etc, by three spiritual practices.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so yes, that's virtual bypass distribution.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah, the concept of forgiveness, or taking of shelter of God, Generally, is born out of…
Govinda Das ji: Listening to high philosophy, which is not actual capacity of that personality.
Govinda Das ji: For example, you know, if somebody has taken 1 lakh rupees from you.
Govinda Das ji: And they're not willing to give you.
Govinda Das ji: And that money matters to you so much.
Govinda Das ji: There is no question of forgiveness, because you need it. It is desperation for you.
Govinda Das ji: Right? If they don't give, you cannot use the philosophy of forgiveness, because you cannot. Because you need that money. But on the other hand, if you have
Govinda Das ji: few crores of rupees, if somebody takes 1 lakh rupees, if they don't give.
Govinda Das ji: You will learn the lesson, okay, I'm not going to give them once again, but I forgive them. Why? Because of the capacity. It's pure practical reality.
Govinda Das ji: Right? Those emotions, if you are not evolved with resources, the emotional resources, the intellectual resources, the physical resources.
Govinda Das ji: The forgiveness is not possible, and therefore it is important what Karan said, you know, he's a spiritualist, he does his satana, he has his Ishtudev.
Govinda Das ji: But when the client is going through.
Govinda Das ji: Focusing on that issue, whether it is… if it is a philosophical issue, then you speak that.
Govinda Das ji: It is a mental issue, then you focus on that, because the reference point will be different for each personality, according to what they are going through. It is not only Annamaya, it is not only Monomaya, it is not only Vigyanamaya. What is the important perspective? I'll give one reference from the Mahabharat.
Govinda Das ji: Dhritarashtra… speaks to… our, Vidura.
Govinda Das ji: And Bhishma speaks to Yudhishtil.
Govinda Das ji: Asking the same question, what is greater?
Govinda Das ji: the question asked by Dritharashtra is asking, destiny, Daiva is greater, or… One's own endeavor is greater.
Govinda Das ji: Vidura says, my dear brother, Endeavor has a limitation, you have to submit to destiny.
Govinda Das ji: You should give respect to the Iva.
Govinda Das ji: And then at the same time, Yudhishtir asked this question, What is superior?
Govinda Das ji: Daivo is superior, or Endeavor is superior.
Govinda Das ji: And Bhishma Dev gave exactly opposite answer. He said, my dear son.
Govinda Das ji: He said endeavor is superior to Daiva.
Govinda Das ji: So when you read that part of the Mahabharat, you may wonder, how is that they're giving contradictory answer? No.
Govinda Das ji: The important principle, answer, It's based upon who is asking the question.
Govinda Das ji: Dhitarashtra is elderly… Endeavor is done with it. He has to focus on the diva.
Govinda Das ji: So, our questions are not based upon facts alone, they are based upon impact.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, it is very important that if you cannot have the capacity to forgive, look for justice.
Govinda Das ji: Right? If you do not have the capacity to take shelter of God, do not imitate taking shelter of God, because it is a process, it is not an abrupt reality. So it's very important to understand where the client, where the patient, where the person who is suffering stands, and what kind of
Govinda Das ji: References a healer has to give.
DhyanShala: Pravoji, sorry to interrupt, I couldn't hear, what was the difference in answer in both cases?
Govinda Das ji: The answer is, Vishma says that Manusha Prayatna saps Mehta Purna, Daiva, will follow it.
Govinda Das ji: And then, Dhritarastra was told by Vidhurraha, Manusha prayer is limited, Daiva is important.
Govinda Das ji: Imagine there is a contradictory answer.
Govinda Das ji: But answer is not important, impact is important. For Dhritarastra, it is very important to hear this one.
Govinda Das ji: Because he's done, he's an elderly person, he has to retire, he has to take, you know, back seat.
Govinda Das ji: Already lost all his sons.
Govinda Das ji: So, he heard that answer. So, Bhishma and…
Govinda Das ji: Vidura studied under the same teacher, Brahas Patiji.
Govinda Das ji: You know, so therefore, they knew the ninyaya of reference point.
Govinda Das ji: It is not simply giving an answer. If somebody's suffering deeply, you do not tell them karma philosophy, you empathize with them.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, answer change not because there is a conflict in philosophy, answer change because there is conflict in perception.
Govinda Das ji: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I would like to just clarify…
Govinda Das ji: Yeah.
Govinda Das ji: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so I don't say that in the first session. So, it happens when every session, the client is bringing in some philosophy, some DTE, etc, and is trying to run away
Dr. Karan Mittal: from addressing his own emotions, thoughts, by using some shloka, some DT, some forgiveness, noble philosophy, etc. That time it happens.
Dr. Karan Mittal: My personal beliefs, or my personal…
Dr. Karan Mittal: thing is outside the therapy room, okay? I don't impose neither, neither
Dr. Karan Mittal: I tell them to become theists or atheists, nothing of that sort happens. But if the client is using spirituality as a bypass to his issues, then the third or fourth session, this kind of conversation happens, when we make it a true
Dr. Karan Mittal: But if you remember the first today, we had discussed that philosophies like Dharma, Punema, karma, they create a sense of hope. So, it's not that we discard it, it's just when the client uses it as a bypass, we try to kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: gauge and try to make some rules there. So that's about the spiritual guidance, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I think this slide will summarize the exercise that we did.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, I'll give you a few questions in your handouts for every kosher and how to go pay it downwards, so this will kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, as I said, you need to switch the kosher. If it's too much of Vidyanmai, bring it to Manumai. Too much of Manomai, go to Vidyanmai. Try to switch the area where the person is
Dr. Karan Mittal: over-utilizing a particular kosher, and that brings in that insight. And once you have switched the kosher, then you can go to the… under my kosher, see where it is localized. Now, during… once the breakout rooms close, someone asks me, what is the importance of
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, using under my Kosha in the therapeutic practice. So at this level, of course, but we cannot say much, but once you localize an emotion in a particular area of your body, if you go from somatic psychotherapy perspective, it helps the body
Dr. Karan Mittal: Dilute the emotion, modify the emotion, increase your threshold towards that particular emotion.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, the coping mechanisms start becoming active. So, if my anger is just in my chest, this is a 5L container having 5L of anger, of course it's overwhelming for me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But by using certain techniques, if I make the container chest plus my abdomen, then in 10 liter of container, there's only 5 liter of hammer. It becomes much more…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, manageable for me. So it increases our threshold to these emotions, and that's why I know my kosher is very important. And of course, from a disease perspective also, if you're storing some emotion
Dr. Karan Mittal: in a particular area of a body for years and decades, that area, because of the cycle, we saw the marine balance, etc, starts showing issues. So it also helps in preventing these kind of psychosomatic issues.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is basically the top-down and bottom-up approach. I'll, of course, put it in the handout that how you go from
Dr. Karan Mittal: the Vidnamay to Anna May, and from Annamay to Vidnamay by just going to the kosher adjacent to it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… yes, Jersey.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so now, now, this is just, again, from a competitive angle. We talk about physical quotient, emotional quotient.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Happiness quotient, intelligence potion, all these quotients are spoken about. Now, if you map these quotients to the punch kosher model, all these koshas were given by Arishis in the form of Punch Kosha model, integrated as one.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we see IQ as a different thing, EQ as a different thing, you know, physical quotient as the way your body performs. Everything is seen differently. But once kosher, if you see it as an integrated perspective, it's all these
Dr. Karan Mittal: quotients merged together to give and wholesome well-being model. So that's this slide about. Adversity quotient is the new quotient, which has recently come in last few years, and it is directly proportional to the amount of happiness you flow. The more threshold you have towards the adversities of life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the more happy you are in your day-to-day experience. So, giving that adversity quotient, you know, that upgrade at every stage of life also becomes an important part of modern imbalance. So that's…
Dr. Karan Mittal: adversity question.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, KJ.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And it can…
Govinda Das ji: Nope.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this is basically…
Dr. Karan Mittal: the structural map of what we saw today, Panchfushas, the Katniaparata, the psychology of the mind, and you also saw that how
Dr. Karan Mittal: Ayurveda Pradneapraadha leading to physical, Adi leading to Vyadi, is also can be seen from the experiential model of Panchosha. So both the schools of philosophy, whether it is the Panchosa, Vedantic school of philosophy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: or the Ayurvedic School of Philosophy, both are showing the same pathway towards development of diseases. As therapists, we work in the Vidnan Maya Anomaya frame and prevent the Anamaya issue.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We can take up questions, maybe, for the day.
Govinda Das ji: Renu Kaja's question.
Renuka Bhuta: yes, Prabhujay. Prabhuji, when you were explaining about, prana, my approach, I was just under… understanding it and connecting with, vata, cuff, and,
Renuka Bhuta: So, is it that we are connect… we are, everything is well connected to, Pranamaya coach, or a different coach?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, see, the answer to this question lies in the explanation of the universal creation itself, because everything in the world is created by Trigona as per Sankhya, and Sankhya and Vashashik formed the baseline of Ayurveda.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes, so your… just specific to your question, yes, part Pitta cuff can be, modeled into pranamay, but it can also be modeled into Manomay and Vidyamaya.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, person of Manu may, probably Bhat will have racing emotions, racing desires.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Kafa will have more stagnant, more dormant kind of, you know, lethargic, because, again, Satvara just tamas is influential over here also. So, Bhataphiktrakuff will impact not only just pranmai, as it impacts under my, it will impact brand, just the length of seeing it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: will change. In the same way, Satwaraja's Tamas will also impact the five pushas. Because baseline, you have to understand, the Indian philosophy is based on a principle of creation.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this principle of creation comes from Satwajasthamas, and these same satvara Rajasthamas make your body also, your mind also, the goodas also, the doshas also. So, when this gets changed, everything else will start changing, right?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's the principle, yeah?
Renuka Bhuta: There was one more question, Prabhuji. I was understanding that Ananda, my coach is from within, okay? But, there are, there are people who are connected to posting things on the media and all those things, so it's.
Govinda Das ji: In fact, in fact.
Renuka Bhuta: What I have, feel that, is it an internal happiness, or is it an external happiness that we are looking for when, when we are talking about Anand Maikosh?
Renuka Bhuta: Because they're talking about validation, and a lot of things that gives them happiness.
Renuka Bhuta: But is it internal happiness when you're talking about Anand Baikosh?
Renuka Bhuta: Or, because there are many students nowadays are more into posting into media, and they feel that, they are very happy when they get those things. Likes and everything. So how do we understand, is it Ananda by Kosh, or is it something else?
Renuka Bhuta: It's not a right thought process.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I think in Anandme Kusha, we discussed, you know, self-confidence is made of self-esteem and self-worth. Being internally self-driven happy is one thing, but you also need happiness
Dr. Karan Mittal: from the external world also. That's self-esteem. So what you're talking about is an imbalance between both. How would a person feel internally happy, and how would the experience come?
Dr. Karan Mittal: the first experience of internal happiness comes from something external, right? Eating a good food.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably mother kind of caring for you, etc. That feeling of happiness is not…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Self-driven, it has to come from something external, right?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, internal happiness is more of a spiritual way of looking at that whole thing, that you have to be internally such a dananda, but that Ananda also comes from something external.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this… what you're talking about, social media, is the imbalance between the self-worth and the self-esteem. Some people who lack… I wouldn't… this is too much of a direct statement, but when self-worth is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of vacuumed or less, then, of course, we'll try to satisfy it by taking things from the external world, posting too much, appreciation.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, the craving for validation, etc. And vice versa also happens.
Renuka Bhuta: So, it should be, I mean, to ask that it should be a balance, it is okay to have an external validation, or it is from internal that we are talking, the happiness point of view.
Renuka Bhuta: Oh…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Both are needed, and both are… both need to be balanced.
Renuka Bhuta: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Self-driven… self-driven happiness, I have not seen a case where a person is fully self-driven happy, okay? So it's very rare. You still need something external to keep it valid. Sorry, probably this adage. Yes.
Govinda Das ji: Yeah, that's what Karan is saying, again. Even up till our last breath.
Govinda Das ji: You know, just like if somebody is suffering from hunger.
Govinda Das ji: You cannot tell them hunger is the state of mind.
Govinda Das ji: No, hunger is a reality.
Govinda Das ji: Similarly, if somebody needs an appointment, appreciation. That is their…
Govinda Das ji: They have a vacuum of receiving appreciation. They have never received appreciation.
Govinda Das ji: So you can… you cannot say, oh, you can derive appreciation within. That will not work. They need to be given that appreciation. If it is not totally available, it is unfortunate.
Govinda Das ji: Right? Then one may say, okay, what can be done in your life
Govinda Das ji: Appreciation is not coming. Can you focus on the next layer of reality?
Govinda Das ji: Right? But that is actually… Very important, therefore, the yoga sutra says, Stiram Sukam Asanam.
Govinda Das ji: Right.
Govinda Das ji: If there is no stability.
Govinda Das ji: If there is no proper position, Asan is not simply yoga asan. Asan is one reality also for them.
Govinda Das ji: of, dances.
DhyanShala: Yes.
Govinda Das ji: Hello? Yes, ma'am.
DhyanShala: Ravuji,
DhyanShala: I have two questions. First one is that, is belief… some… if someone is hardcore into some ideology.
DhyanShala: Or some framework he believes.
DhyanShala: Maybe he's driven by emotions, or monomag.
DhyanShala: Or, by logic.
DhyanShala: began, man. So, is it possible to change
DhyanShala: Is belief system, if that belief system is impacting His mental or physical state.
DhyanShala: If yes, then how?
DhyanShala: And my second question is to Dr. Mithel.
DhyanShala: Can I get the answer first, and then I'll opt. Second.
Govinda Das ji: Yes, so the… again, therefore.
Govinda Das ji: from the Dharmic perspective, from the Dharma perspective, everybody has an opportunity to grow from wherever they are.
Govinda Das ji: No, it doesn't matter how radical one is.
Govinda Das ji: Right? So the dose of medicine will differ.
Govinda Das ji: But the point is… Because…
Govinda Das ji: our constitutional identity is full of knowledge, full of bliss, full of eternality. If they cannot manage in this lifetime, like, one of the best ways, like, when you study Jyotes Shia, we did not get into Jyotes Shastra, because Shin.
Govinda Das ji: Rather than… it is not a science of prediction. When science of prediction is given more importance to science of indication, then it becomes problematic.
Govinda Das ji: Right? When you study Jyotish Shastra, you'll understand, you know, that, their karma, like, simple example is given. Like, if somebody has a $100,000 loan.
Govinda Das ji: And their salary is soulless, So now the focus is not to… Remove all the load.
Govinda Das ji: But minimize the…
Govinda Das ji: If I cannot completely pay off, at least minimize it from $100,000, let me make it $40,000. From $40,000, let me make $20,000. Let me say, he's still not able to pay off the loan, but still they are minimizing.
Govinda Das ji: So, therefore, Whatever Kosha one is in, whatever Guna one is in, whatever Prakriti one is there.
Govinda Das ji: the Dharma Shastras always give that space that they can move from here to the higher realms of reality. Therefore, the concept of yoga comes in.
Govinda Das ji: Yoga is the process through which…
Govinda Das ji: One can overcome whatever conditioning, may not be in this lifetime, may not be tomorrow, but certainly, for sure, they will go back to their original identity.
DhyanShala: Indeed. May I ask too, Dr. Nitin,
Govinda Das ji: Yep.
DhyanShala: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
DhyanShala: So, first day, I think first or second class, we, we have heard very beautiful line that non-judgment
DhyanShala: is a skill. Being non-judgmental is a skill.
DhyanShala: So, maybe this may be the personal question for you also. So, being a therapist, how you…
DhyanShala: Keep a separation between your personal life as well as professional life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That means…
DhyanShala: Can you take up same lens in your personal as well as professional? Definitely, if not, then how you manage that?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I think it comes with lots of self-work, the 500…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Traumas myself, or 100 belief systems myself.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I will, of course.
Dr. Karan Mittal: judge the client with those 100 beliefs, and 100 traumas, and 100 whatever vasnas and scaras and Sanskrit terms. So it comes with lots of self-work, going, you know, reducing that 100 to 50, 60, whatever, whatever is possible.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also, it's a skill that you develop, that if I belong to a particular religion or a particular belief system, I learn it as a skill to keep that hat out of the therapist's room. That's the second thing. And also, the third thing, that I also, as a therapist, go to a therapist once in a while to get
Dr. Karan Mittal: my things checked, which I said it's nowadays mandatory also to keep on renewing your license, so that all these small, small things, what I notice for my clients, someone else notices it for me and points it out to make a distance to you. It could be, like, going for therapy, it could also be case consultation. We also go into
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, if there's a case which we are not able to talk, then we talk to our teachers, or… and take their insights of what can be done, etc. So, like, someone said to me that I could figure it out till restlessness. How did you know that
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, there was a layer below it also. That's me going… like, I do the same process with my teachers, that I came with the clientele here, now you tell me what. So, these are 3-4 things that we do for self-work also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also trying reducing our Sanskara's Vasnau belief system.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It happens eventually.
DhyanShala: Then how you keep a check that this,
DhyanShala: This lens of therapist should not come into your personal life, like in your relations with your family members.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's, it's, it's like a switch.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Eventually, you will start developing a switch. When I'm in the therapist's room, that switch is on. When I'm back home, I cannot keep on analyzing a person continuously. Now, my brain will get exhausted, so I cannot keep on analyzing a family member, a friend, etc. So you… by experience, you learn to switch it off when you are with your
Dr. Karan Mittal: Only. That happens, like, it's a switch-off switch only.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. Any other questions?
Dr. Karan Mittal: I think we are done to OG, I guess. All questions and answers.
Govinda Das ji: So you'll send a thank you for all your attention, for joining with us for…
Govinda Das ji: 5 sessions, almost 10 to 11 hours.
Govinda Das ji: And, we can keep the group for some more days, if you have any questions, comments.
Govinda Das ji: If you want to ask anything, you're welcome to ask to get more Detailed understanding, either Go on.
Govinda Das ji: I don't know.
Sattvastha Ventures: Before we conclude, I would just like to request all of you all to just keep your videos on. We are trying to take screenshots, and we may even tag you with your consent.
Sattvastha Ventures: So, if you can please do that for us.
Sattvastha Ventures: I'm very grate.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yep.
Sattvastha Ventures: Thanks a lot, everybody.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry?
Sattvastha Ventures: Yeah, just thanking everybody for accommodating with this request.
Sattvastha Ventures: And we are concluding this session.
Sattvastha Ventures: and the seminar. And as Prabhuji said, the group will be open, so any of your doubts can be…
Sattvastha Ventures: as directed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thank you, everyone. Namaste.
Govinda Das ji: Stay.
Sattvastha Ventures: Let's do…
Renuka Bhuta: Thank you.
DhyanShala: Thank you.
Lavina Shewaramani: Thank you very much. Thank you.